we're gonna go through all the basics of
final cut pro i'm gonna make it really
easy for you but we're also gonna build
habits so you can edit professional
videos down the line my name is tyler
stallman let's get started so first a
tour of the interface here is an
existing project that's already underway
over here on the left you're going to
notice a bunch of beautiful footage by
the way as we look through this i can't
take credit for these shots these are
courtesy of stoxy united sponsor of
today's video and more about stocks
later over here in your browser you've
got everything you might end up using in
your project so i've already loaded this
in i'll show you how to do that in a sec
but just to give you a sense that this
is where you preview it this is just
like the staging ground of like figuring
out what you've got
i've also got music later in here
everything goes in the browser and
that's where you preview stuff and by
the way if you can't see enough of what
you're looking at you can resize all
these areas by grabbing the between
lines you can also press the command
minus command plus to zoom in and out
and make these clips bigger or smaller
and there's a couple tabs on the browser
that opens up your libraries so in here
i've got a few other projects open so
this is a completed commercial project
for a skincare brand that we did it
gives you a better sense of what a
completed timeline might look like but
we're not there yet so we're going to go
back into our final cut for beginners
project and close the libraries for now
here in the middle this is our viewer
that is currently showing us our
beautiful stock footage and that's just
going to play whatever you have selected
so right now it's playing the bottom of
the screen if i click over here in the
browser again we're going to start
seeing stuff from the browser by the way
see i'm just like moving my mouse and
it's scrubbing around through the clip
if you don't like that some people find
it confusing to move around that quickly
you can press s
that turns off scrubbing and now you
won't get that effect as your mouse
moves around the screen instead uh you'd
have to like click and drag but so yeah
i'm going to keep it on and press s
again and now wherever my mouse is on a
clip it'll show me that exact frame here
in the viewer moving to the right of the
screen we've got the inspector right now
it's showing us color adjustments we can
make on this but there's all sorts of
stuff in here again tabs will show us
the way this one gives us different
things like opacity if you want to
change how much you see through a clip
or the
zoom amount
basically all the properties about a
clip are over here in the inspector and
you can switch between different things
like right now this would transform the
clip and this will show me specific
details about it i can get more details
down here there's a lot to see don't get
overwhelmed you don't need to worry
about it much yet um the first things
we'll like we'll leave it on the video
inspector tab
to start with and then down here below
at the bottom this is our timeline this
is what editing is it's putting a bunch
of clips in a row so that they play back
as a sequence so it's not just one long
clip we've got some different layers of
them on top of each other we've got
music on the bottom and i'll show you
how to use it in two seconds but for now
i'll just keep scrubbing back and forth
because i like seeing this footage but
um also worth knowing is that wherever
you've clicked last you'll see this very
subtle blue border and that's how you
know which of these panels is selected
so right now you can tell the timeline
if i click the viewer there's a little
bit of a bluish purple up here at the
top if i click the inspector depending
which panel is selected
different keys and shortcuts will do
different things in that area so for
example a basic shortcut you could have
guessed if i click on the inspector and
i press command plus it will zoom in
command minus will zoom out if i do that
over here in the browser it'll do the
same thing it'll zoom in and out of my
clips so that's the overall interface
structure of final cut pro
and i might be moving a little bit
quickly but don't worry i will show you
how we put this all together and if it's
overwhelming just re-watch this video
once you're done with it because there's
a lot of details in here and i know it's
hard to absorb in real time but i want
to keep this video short enough that uh
you have time to watch it twice okay so
uh let's let's put this all together now
let's leave final cut for a second go
back to the finder and set this all up
from scratch so first i'm going to use
an external disk if you're using your
internal you might fill it up really
quickly so an external ssd is always
helpful and i'm going to create a new
folder call it final cut pro
getting started
and inside of there i'm going to create
a folder called video and another one
called audio
and sometimes i need one called images
too whatever kinds of media that's how i
sort things but the sorting you got to
kind of do it in the finder before
you've set everything else up so now we
go when we launch final cut pro and this
is what it's going to look like when you
haven't done anything yet just a pretty
big blank screen we're gonna go file new
library i've explained libraries in a
previous video and why i use a different
library for every single project unless
all the videos share footage but usually
new library every project that video
will help a lot the link is in the
description below and i usually name it
the same thing as the folder
and let's minimize final cut and look at
what that did so now there is a library
inside of our project folder and this is
how i kind of organize things before we
customize the library or build anything
there's one preference i recommend
changing based on the way that i edit
and that's in the import section of
preferences i'm going to change it to
leave files in place so that allows all
of those folders we just created to stay
organized the way that you made them if
you do copy to library it will make
duplicate files inside of a library file
and
apple says it's easier i find it a
little harder to let apple manage your
media so we're going to leave files in
place oh and williman preferences i just
want to point out in the playback
section this background render option
this is kind of significant for how
final cut works and how it's so fast
whenever you stop working final cut just
starts to render your video so that when
you export it it's like ready to go this
can slow down your machine if your
machine is really like overtaxed because
it's rendering all the time but if you
have a reasonably fast machine then your
final export is super speedy so
try to keep it on if you can but if you
find your machine slowing down you can
turn it off it depends i just want to
point this out for later okay i'm gonna
leave it on back to editing so now let's
get some videos in here i'm gonna go
back to the finder where i was a moment
ago and here are the videos that i
downloaded from stoxxy i'm just going to
select them all and again file
management starts in the finder and i'm
going to drag them to the video folder
that i created so now i know where they
all are doesn't really matter what
they're named i don't have to worry
about any of that now let's go back into
final cut and there's two ways to do
this one you can click import which it's
good to see this import dialog because
it shows you all the options and all the
preferences you could use
looks a little more complicated i'll
show you the easy way in a sec but again
same thing that i don't want to copy to
library that could create duplicates i'm
going to leave files in place i'm just
going to navigate to it which is on my
external drive here you can see a
preview of everything you're about to
import lots of preferences over here on
the right good to know this in the
future we're not going to use it today
so instead i'm actually going to close
this import dialog
go back to the finder and i'm going to
click and drag this whole video folder
onto this date now we haven't talked
about the date yet but the date is just
the default name for an event an event
is a folder i this is this is a place
where people can get confused so an
event in final cut pro is effectively
just a folder i usually only actually
have one event per project i don't even
rename it so i'm going to just leave
that what it is and inside you'll notice
it created a keyword do this little key
it's because the keyword is the name of
the folder i imported so now when i go
back to the finder and click and drag my
audio folder to the same place
i have all my audio is keyworded now our
browser has a bunch of media to work
with but our timeline it's still empty
down here so you can either click new
project or it's good to know where it is
file
new project and i usually name my
projects the same thing as the library
unless i have like different versions of
edits or something a project is
basically a timeline final cut made some
of their naming of this stuff a little
bit confusing like i think some people
think of the library as projects and
some people think of projects as
timelines
the names are a little confusing so just
look at the way that i use them this
project
is the timeline we're about to create so
there are some preferences to look at
here right now i was about to create a
vertical video that's not what this is
this is 4k footage and i'm going to be
doing it at 24 frames per second
rounded down and those the only things
you really need to look at here is the
actual resolution make sure it matches
whatever it is you shot and that the
frame rate again is like similar to what
you're using the rest of this you don't
really have to worry about it most of
the time you can also use automatic
settings which will do it based on what
you import in the timeline but i always
like to customize it and we say okay and
now we have a timeline at the bottom
hopefully you're with me so far so now
if i am looking at the library you can
see there is a project in our library
there's no footage in a project yet and
now watch they create the fastest edit
ever so i'm just gonna select all and
i'm going to drag it all into the
timeline and because the stoxy footage
looks so good i don't have to do
anything else and it kind of looks like
a movie already and to make it faster
here i'll do this like change duration
and make everything half a second okay
and now we've got a very cool edit and
you know about soxy already because
they're awesome not just for sponsoring
this video but they're a community of
filmmakers and photographers
including yours truly that provide
really good quality art that's easy for
you to license for your next project so
that means it's royalty-free very
stress-free you can basically use it for
anything without getting worried about
whether it's covered by the license or
not but if you need they do also have
extended licenses market freezes and
exclusivity so you can just talk to them
about whatever your specific needs are
but the basic license covers most things
the search is easy to use and stoxy has
powerful discovery tools so it's easy to
find exactly the shots that you're
looking for for your project whatever it
is the quality of work there is really
next level one cool feature is that they
shoot in like narrative sequences a lot
of the time so you'll be able to find
multiple shots to tell a complete story
so it's not just one offs like the shots
can link together and keep some kind of
common style location or characters
throughout your footage and stocks these
contributors are a community unlike any
other it's a cooperative so everybody
actually has a say in how the companies
run and that means that it's really
allowed it to thrive and that's why when
i call them artists
i mean it and it's not all the cool
trendy lifestyle stuff i showed you here
you can also check them out to find you
know great business office environments
for landscapes just head over to stocks
click the link in the description below
and thanks doxie for sponsoring this
video i really like what you do now back
to final cut all right now let's set it
for real that was a bit of a cheat
throwing at all my timeline let's delete
all that select all delete now we're
going to go back to the browser and
select some good moments that we like so
uh one way you could do that is just by
mousing over things again we have the
scrub tool on i could just move and i
could just click and drag and that
selects the area that i want to use and
i could either drag that down to the
timeline or i told you i was going to
build some good habits for you guys
we're going to click on it make sure
it's yellow and then press e that is the
key that will drop it to the end of the
timeline it's usually how i'm adding
clips into it if you're not the kind of
person that uses shortcuts now's the
time to start you should really be using
shortcuts so i'll keep telling them to
you if navigating and if you haven't
figured out how to navigate the browser
yet again i've got the scrubber thing on
so i just moved through it till i like a
moment maybe i want to turn around here
so right at the turnaround
i could press play and that'll preview
it in real time she's just looking
around okay cool so maybe that's what i
want to use the other way to insert
things is as you're playing
you can press the i key for in and when
you're done press o and that section is
now selected so in and out is the range
of the clip that's going to be used and
now when i press the e key again
that'll drop it into the end of the
timeline and even if i move my playhead
like if i move the playhead forward and
i'm going to use the next clip here and
i say in and i say out and then i press
e it still jumps to the end of the
timeline a tip i've mentioned in other
videos is that as you're previewing
stuff over here can be really helpful to
instead of just adding it directly to
the timeline press you're in
and out and then press the f key and you
see there's a little green line here
that means it's been favorited so later
i could go back and i could sort by all
my favorites and then you can just refer
back to like all the favorite moments of
the whole shoot that you've got but
that's a little advanced for now for now
we'll just keep dropping them into the
timeline as you're playing through your
browser when you hit the spacebar it
will actually just keep playing from one
clip to the other so in our case again
this looks sort of edited as it just
plays through if it's not playing from
one to the other there is something
called loop by the way i forget where
things are in menus sometimes so you can
always click help and i'm going to look
for loop oh there it is it's in playback
loop or more importantly the shortcut
for it is
command l so uh that will just keep
playing the same clip over and over when
it gets to the end you can see it just
looped
i prefer to keep it on playing from one
clip to the next clip now let's skip
ahead i'm going to look at the timeline
that i already edited and now it looks a
little different you can see there are
some layers so a very important concept
in final cut is that there is something
called a primary timeline which is
designated by this darker strip here in
the overall timeline and that's really
where you start like in a basic edit
like this you could do everything with
just the primary timeline and you don't
have to start having stacks of different
clips on top of each other by the way if
you're coming from a different video
editing software this is probably what's
going to trip you up more than anything
is the magnetic timeline but
if you're new to video editing this is
the thing that will make you never want
to leave final cut pro because the
magnetic timeline is the best i do see
youtube videos showing people how to
disable the magnetic timeline
if you're doing that
stop using final cut like that
it's like the whole point
of the the reason that it's so quick to
work with like final cut isn't just fast
because it's optimized for mac hardware
it's fast because the metaphors
accelerate your workflow and have you
build up momentum as you go it kind of
wants you
to make the next edit as soon as
possible and pushes you towards it and i
always appreciate that so i can always
finish and edit it faster in final cut
than in any other software so thanks
final cut now magnetic timeline what am
i talking about that's apple's marketing
term for the fact that if i pull this
out you can see things either snap
together or snap open it either makes
space for or closes the space of any
clip that i add to it now you're
probably like why would that be
confusing to anybody that seems so
simple well here i'm going to add a
piece of music
underneath it and now here's probably
the main thing that trips people up with
the magnetic timeline music is now you
know it just like plays through the
whole clip as things go by it just keeps
playing and um if i grab this first clip
and move it the music comes with it this
is very different from how other editors
work and basically as things get stacked
on top of each other they create these
tiny little lines so you can see this
one is going down the music it's going
up if you're ever grabbing clips and
moving them and they're connected in a
way you don't want it's really easy to
change it you just have to remember the
shortcut which is command option hold
those down and then just click on
wherever it is you want to move the
connection to so i'm going to click on
the music and now the connection has
moved to this other clip or in the case
of this b-roll i could you know these
connect a little bit more right this
person might be what these aren't the
same shoes it's not the same person okay
but i want to connect these i can
command option click and now the line is
connected there so those two are
together this makes it so much easier to
not make mistakes when you're editing in
final cut and it's the hardest thing for
me to go back to let's say resolve or
premiere
is that you can make a change earlier in
your edit and it kind of breaks
everything later in your edit whereas
final cut keeps everything together and
you can keep moving quickly and just
trust the software to not let things
fall apart anyway this is this is like
why i keep using final cut forever
because the metaphor just makes a lot of
sense to my brain so right now the
length of the clips that are playing
like their duration was set by the in
and out points that we originally
established but
after we've added them all to the
timeline we probably want to make some
changes now i have a special way of
doing that that i didn't learn for a
little while and so i'm going to pass it
along to you oh wait first one little
thing the music doesn't take up the
whole length of the video right now so
here's one way to do it this is the the
first way i learned is you just can
click and grab the end of any clip or
any piece of music and drag it to the
link that you want to use you're
probably going to keep using that
forever it is always useful but it's
definitely not the fastest way to do
things usually i've added too much of
clips like they're longer than i want
them to be and i want to trim them down
so
let's say that bike shot i want to be a
little bit shorter so i click on the
clip and i look at where the playhead is
and when i press option right square
bracket kind of an obscure shortcut but
it will trim everything to the right of
where the playhead was on that selected
clip and then i could also do that at
the beginning and i could press option
left square bracket and it trims
everything to the left this is called
the ripple delete because the changes
ripple through the rest of the timeline
like everything else slips into place as
i remove that little section in fact i
use it so much that i like to go into
the commands and i customize them and
like the only customization i do is i
make it so that just pressing that
square bracket that does the trim
instead of needing the option key by the
way my philosophy on customizing keys in
general is don't do it too much because
you're gonna go on somebody else's
computer someday and you won't know how
to use it so uh i just make a few small
changes
like removing those modifiers so now
we've tightened up our edit and it plays
back at a speed that we like
we can kind of finish it right let's
like tweak the things at the end and
make it exactly what we want okay so for
example this shot i believe this is
actually shot on film and it just
doesn't quite match our other stuff so
i'm going to use the inspector layer to
make a few changes to this so that
it is more in line with the others i
don't want to remove it so i make sure
that it's selected there'll be that
yellow border around it and then inside
of the inspector i can do a few things
uh first you can see that there are
black borders on this because this is a
four by three ratio that's the
super eight i think you can see the
camera menu there's the cameraman in
here so um it is cropped uh in a
different way than the rest of the
footage so to make it match i'm gonna
click on the zoom slider and drag it
until i've lost those edges which is
kind of boring i know i'm like cutting
out the cool film stuff a bit but uh
just for this example i can still see
some on the left there so i got to go
just a little bit more
that is not actually making it any
better but
it does match now other things we might
want to make match uh commonly are the
colors so we're going to click on this
little color inspector tab right now and
i've got a different default here if you
want to check this out you can go in
your preferences and you can get a
variety of defaults depending on what
you choose as your color correction
default thing i don't like the color
board color wheels are standard like
that's the industry standard so
i changed that so that this is what i
see at first and this is looking very
blue compared to everything i mean it's
quite a blue shot so i'm going to start
by grabbing my midtones
warm them up a whole bunch then i just
look at it like next to the shots beside
it it just feels more at home it's a
little less out of place
also maybe a little darker in the
mid-tones and next in the inspector tab
we got to know about the audio i've only
got music in here none of these clips
have their own audio so i'm going to
click on the music to show it to you
and
the most important thing is volume i
mean do i need to tell you that you can
just move it up and down but you've got
to click on the audio thing to know
about that um also there are effects
that you can add so for example um in
addition to just turning it down
sometimes you might want to like
uniformly raise or lower the whole
volume inside of this button here are
all of the effects so i know there's a
plug-in called gain gain is just like
volume and i can drag this over here and
i can say okay everything gets turned
down by i don't know whatever mostly i'm
just trying to show you that all the
effects are over here so um you can also
apply video effects so for example
there's a bunch of color stuff that's
very helpful here you can put luts on
top so if i click and drag that onto
here now in the inspector i can see some
lut options and i'm going to apply one
of my luts which you can download if you
want and it just gives it a bit of a
film look to kind of match that other
film shot there's tons of effects in
here dig around see what you can find
but then also right beside it there are
transitions try to keep your transitions
kind of basic don't go crazy with them
that's like an editing tip but we are
going to use one here we are going to
fade out to black at the end using fade
to color i can grab these small edges to
make it longer or shorter click on it
i've got to set my mid point to the end
otherwise it would start to fade
halfway through the or finish fading
halfway through the clip so i want to
finish fading at the end of the clip and
now i play it
and it fades to black now before you
rewind this video and start watching
from the beginning i'm going to tell you
one more important tip like this is
actually quite important and can slow
people down a lot if they don't get it
with final cut final cut creates these
big cache files that's what the
rendering was doing remember when we
were in the preferences and we disabled
or enabled depending on how you work
background render that's creating those
giant cache files so we click on our
library you can see for example that it
is in the library there is 1.4 gigs it's
not very big yet but this can grow a lot
like hundreds of gigs eventually to keep
everything organized again this is with
the library selected go to storage
locations and modify settings
for the media i'm just going to choose
like the root folder for the whole
project and then for cache i'm going to
choose that same folder and now when i
go back to the finder this is the cache
file and you can see how big it is it's
not actually that big but now you can
just quickly delete it if you ever need
to make room for things that cache is
just speeding up final cut it's not
necessary for the edit but it can be
enormous
so it's good to know where to find it
and how to delete it you can also if
you've kept it in your library go to
file delete generated library files and
there's some options here to delete
cache and other stuff now i know that
was a lot but i've got a playlist that
will walk you through a whole bunch of
other editing tips to make this easy for
you editing should be fun it shouldn't
be too hard it's a lot of the reason i
like final cut pro because it keeps it
fun thanks for watching guys i'll see
you in the next video